hello everyone welcome to actin flab
guest stream number 19.1 it's march 25th
and we are here with marco falcon and we
are going to be discussing the recent
paper extended predictive minds do
markov blankets matter so if you're
watching live please feel free to
put
comments or questions in the live chat
and hopefully we can address them
and marco really appreciate you joining
looking forward to hearing about this
paper and your lines of research so
would be awesome to hear an introduction
and take it away
okay hi everyone so i'm mark of akin i
actually am a phd candidate in italy
and
steep paper basically is an attempt to
understand
what was going on
in the active inference literature with
the externalism internalism debate from
a philosophical perspective
so i
studied philosophy for the most part i'm
not super mathematically savvy and i
have basically a background in
embodied extended cognition
and i stumbled upon the papers by whole
year after another and i
wanted to understand what was going on
with
the mark of blanket talk
and so i wrote a paper about it to to
understand what was going on
and to try to suggest that maybe
that much emphasis on markov blanket is
a bit misplaced
and yes
that's it for a general introduction for
the paper i think
and
then here for any question or any doctor
okay cool so maybe um i'll just ask some
questions and we'll just see where it
goes
for somebody who was
unfamiliar with
extended cognitive
processes or the state of the art maybe
outside of active inference just what is
this area how are people looking at it
outside of the active inference fep
angle and like what is the contemporary
state of that area
so okay
so the extended cognition stuff
say officially is something that
spawn out a paper by clark and chalmers
in the early 2000s basically
and their original idea was
as i understand it at least this that
sometimes at least
you interact with the environment in a
way such that part of cognition happens
in the environment itself so my go-to
example is using pen and paper to them
off
when you use pen and paper to do math
you write down partial results
and that scrap of paper is working as
a piece of your working memory it's just
that it's not inside your brain is
around you on your
desk or whenever you're doing enough
and so that was basically the original
idea and from that
there has been a reach collaboration
with people like richard minari
suggesting that
actually ddtdd
we should think that
extended cognitive processes as
processes that transform our cognitive
capacities is not just
more stuff more memory more symbols but
new stuff new capacities new symbols new
uh
cognitive processes that take place in
the interaction in between the subject
and the environment
so we have that line of research and
then you have a more say an active line
of research that
tends to stress the edd idea that
basically all cognition takes place in
the world interacting with affordances
or interacting with
your surrounding environments
but i'm not super
expert on that line of research on the
extended miner a bit more
conservative so
the punchline would be this that
sometimes
stuff in the external world really is in
the most literal sense possible a cog of
the machinery that does your
thinking that is
clearest and the most forceful way in
which i'm able to put a deity of
the extended mind
and of course sorry once you have this
idea on the table the question is okay
but where
when where does it stop
is pen and paper is in but i don't know
are our cell phones in
our
are books in here at my uh left
you might not be able to see it but
there is a big library with a lot of
books there right are all those books
part of my memory probably not
but you need some sort of
and that's the full mark of blood of
course so i'll leave it
like this
well i i like this you said it was like
a cog and it's kind of like cognition so
it's right there in the word even though
that's a little bit of a word play um
and also very interesting about the more
is different like we're not just
augmenting the computer with a bigger
hard drive or more ram it truly can be
different and so i think maybe we could
return to this idea of like what is the
space of the adjacent possible for
cognitive systems especially if they
compose in these non-linear ways
but could you maybe
walk us through
some of the pieces of the paper like
what
brought you to the introduction what
brought you to writing this
paper on markov blankets and then what
did you sort of weave together in the
introduction how did you clash him in
the middle and then where did you leave
us at the end
so did you walk through to the paper is
something
not super sure i'll be able to do
satisfactory at least
so
ddddd first step
was to
what motivated me was to try and figure
out what was going on between andy clark
jakob hoey ramstad
and mark of blankets of course
and what i wanted to argue basically was
something like this
that even if you set aside dddd works by
yellow barineburg and others or menarian
gillettes that
tend to give you this sort of message
like we have a
perfectly fine mathematical concept of
markup blankets
and then a strange concept of recent
blankets that is a big mathematical and
a bit ontological and we are not really
sure what it is even if you leave this
sort of worries aside
what i wanted to say is that the way in
which markov blankets are used
uh for when it comes to discussing the
extended mind stuff uh is very limited
to the specific application but
for the extended mind the usage of
markup blankets
is not really useful
does
nothing
of particular value
and
tends to give a big headache to the
people that are not interactive in
france so i would recommend not using
them
if the main arguments
i think
there is no main argument doctor i think
i have three arguments
that are well first
in order to find a mark of blankets
it seems that you must already know what
is inside
if you think about a graph
there is
no way in which i can give you a graph
and and just ask you okay please show me
where is the marker blanket in there i
need to tell you of
about which node i'm interested in right
so you must already know what is inside
and when it comes to demand cognitive
machinery knowing what is inside is
knowing
which are the cards
which will presumably include
brain plus maybe stuff in the
environment pen and paper and whatever
and if you already know that which you
must already know in order to find the
relevant markup blanket
that intuitively you already know
whether the mind extends or not
and if you already know whether the mind
extends or not
you know whether it stands or not there
is no new
you this is a no new piece of
information to to be gained by thinking
about whether mind extends or not in
terms of marker blanket that is the e4
the first argument
the second one which is a bit messy
could i just pause there make a comment
on the first one just okay
awesome so
though the markov blanket uh if only it
were like the blankets on our bed and
you could pick it up and it was a
blanket whether it was inside the box or
around the box or whatever
that's not
really how they are defined it's really
like a co-partitioning of internal and
external states with respect to a
blanket or a blanket with respect to
some other internal and external states
so the blanket states are the ones that
make two other sets of states internally
external conditionally independent and
so it's not that a node can be even in a
purely statistical sense so without
getting into the whole what do they
physically map onto
a given node is not like a blanket state
or an internal state it's a blanket
state with respect to some other states
because it's part of this partitioning
that's co-instantiated at the same
moment so it's an excellent point where
if you know what your system of
interests internal states are
then you can talk about what states
blanket them with respect to some other
states
but if the question is about the
extended mind and what are the internal
states of mind then there's kind of this
catch 22 cat in the hat scenario where
if you knew
where to
even focus
you would have already sort of addressed
the question up front just to sort of
unpack that and connect it to some of
the other ways we've talked about it
yeah that's a great unboxing
the keyword you said and that i forgot
to set
is the system you're interested in
uh why i want to do to focus on this
right now because
the uh extended mind stuff
is supposed to be hyper realistic
uh the idea is not that
uh i mean we can treat pen and paper as
if they were a form of external memory
that is something you can do
but is not the claim that interests me
clark menari
the claim is that
that interests me clark and minari is
that pen and paper really are with the
capital r a on of r
really are a piece of memory in the
external world
right
they are memory in the same sentence in
which
parts of your neural activation or
memory system are memory
that is ddd relevant claim so there is
nothing
observer dependent or interest
dependence
is
really a hardcore metaphysics about how
the word actually is independently about
what you know about it
so that's the point that i should
probably have meet sooner
well you made it in the paper with uh
the direction of identification runs
from target variables to markup blankets
not the other way around
so yeah
yeah
so that's the first argument the second
one is very muddy and also very
dependent on the
how the editors were on the extended
minds
and mark of blanca develop
but the point is basically this
uh
that from the very beginning
that would be probably who is
2016 paper the self-evidencing brain
uh
d message look there are
many possible blankets and we have
somehow to choose one
uh that sort of message get got through
the literature here
and the way in which yeah hui
and others tried to
single out the super special blankets
among the many possible was to look at
south of the dancing in the long run
about
keeping your
keeping yourself close to your set point
in the long run
and their idea as i understood it
was to say that well the machinery of
the mind
is identical to the machinery that keeps
yourself near your set point in the long
run
and that sounds persuasive from a free
energy principle perspective
but it's not super persuasive if you are
not
very into the free energy principle
because there is a lot of stuff that
keep us alive and kicking in the long
run our liver
our guts
our kidneys and prima faction
none of those organs does thinking in an
intelligible sense
and so did you worry here
that
probably is never actually stated in the
paper is that we are confusing
cognizing
in some broad and fuzzy sense with
staying alive
i mean
i've nothing
against the claim that living things
tend to cognize or tend to behave
intelligently
plants do behave intelligently even if
very slowly
says behave intelligently
but i'm not super sure about
equating the two
and that would be probably my second
point
okay let's
stay on this because that's also a great
point so
if not
one and the same as staying alive
what other perspectives on cognition
might there be like what is thinking
other than staying alive or what is it
that for example the neurons and the
glia are doing that the um
cartilage in the knee is not doing
a fascial processing information would
be a different dancer if you take tiny
or at least censor inflammation
so
that
that's the question i'm struggling with
right now
and my two cents would be
this
that's
we have a big problem because
not because we don't have a definition
of cognition but because we have too
many definition of cognition we have too
many research programs
telling us what cognition is so you have
ddd
classic
cognitive science what is cognition well
symbol manipulation when you go with the
connection is what is cognition well
vector transformation sub-symbolic
computation then you have the
inactivists
what is cognition um
sense making
slash autonomy
uh ecological psychologists what has
cognition while interacting skillfully
with affordances and so on and so forth
and my big problem is that
no one here is clearly wrong
no one is obviously dead wrong and that
thing clearly cannot be cognition
and so what i think i would suggest is a
sort of pluralism
about cognition cognition is not a
single thing it's not like dancing what
is dancing well moving your arms yes
sometimes but sometimes dancing might
even be staying still in a certain piece
of art there might be
some regimented stainless steel as a
part of dancing
and that would be the analogy
so
something that gets done in a variety of
ways
none of which
seems to apply to kidneys livers cloves
and that sort of things
if i can layer
one more sort of um
[Music]
and or there's the experience and the
phenomenology
of us as ourselves and as people and
then there's sort of the behaviorism
or at the very least animal behavioral
sciences or just behavioral studies in
general
which is like from the outside looking
at a system and so there's this
gap
between like us doing the
um thinking about cognition
and the experience of that thinking
about cognition and then the question
about recognizing cognition in
other people in children in non-humans
et cetera and so like i really like that
how you lay like there's the symbol the
sub-symbolic inactive and then no one
disagrees no one is saying that bacteria
make bad decisions on the whole they're
here aren't they and no one's saying
like a tree doesn't have a metabolic
coupling with a fungus and no one's
saying that the fungus doesn't defuse
signals
but then the
aspects of these systems
that people focus their regime of
attention on
and where they choose to start their
talks and what they decide to talk about
and what experiments they design
that frames the discussion
about cognition
that's a wonderful way to do it
and i'm a bit
sad because the paper
about cognition has already been
submitted
if i hadn't submitted it already i would
have stolen the framing part because
it's wonderful i said
that said
so there are two things i'd like to say
about
that so the first one is
no one really disagrees i'm not sure i
think that there is some genuine
disagreement
so the hardcore ecological psychologist
i believe
and feel free to correct me if there are
any ecological set of colleges really
think that cognition is interacting with
affordances
full stop
and that there is no symbol manipulation
going on in the background
and
i the classic cognitivists i think
really think that cognizing justice
manipulation manipulating symbols in the
background so there are genuine
disagreements
uh
what i'm
not super sure about is whether
those disagreements
are solvable in the sense that you can
provide a master argument or even master
experiments
uh
from which you can just read off oh the
ecological psychologist was wrong
classic cognitiveness was
right
i think that the best we can do is
accept some form of plurality about what
cognition is and perhaps but i'm not
super sure we might have to accept that
there may be things that are neither
determinately cognitive neither
determinately not cognitive
i mean
plants
do behave do cope with their environment
well
i'm not entirely comfortable about
saying that there are
cognizers in the exact same sense in
which i am recognizer
maybe it's just because their behavior
is very slow if compared to mine maybe
it's because i have certain
cultural prejudices which i mean they
exist
and
dddd
call
calling something a cognizer is
influenced by your prejudices if you go
back to the
early analytic philosopher pretty much
no one votes animals think and now is
unbelievable that's someone
for someone to have that position so
so there is that but it's not super
holdout
but the big message would probably be
this put simply there might be something
[Music]
something of a gray area between
thinking with symbols surely cognitive
and
being a rock really not cognitive the
sort of big gray area in which you have
intelligence coping with the environment
coping with the environment well
adaptability
flexibility
but still
not
not be really sure about whether there
is some cognition with the capital c
going on in there
and that's the first thing
then you also mentioned polio and
consciousness but
i am very scared about that stuff
okay so
another interesting piece as evidenced
by the um the um
think about what to say carefully don't
want to say that it's a lane we could
veer off into but right that is a more
purely philosophical
discussion whereas
neurobehavioral studies and cognitive
science frames itself as science
and in science usually we think about
like unique explanations predictions the
ability to design and control and
perturb systems
so
is this
science what kind of science what are we
looking for here in a cognitive model
and how do we resolve or accommodate
this tension between like unique
explanations and predictions which is
the
bedrock of one type of science
with
the call for pluralism
that you just made
i think that the answer here is
do nothing
in the sense that
the call for pluralism
is not a very
not a call
cognitive science is splintered you have
everyone doing its own thing in its own
lab
there is cooperation
uh in the sense that
uh
i mean
the various research groups are not
entirely isolated is not the case that
people working on mirror neurons know
nothing about connectionism or
classical computationalism or whatever
there is some communication
but on the face of it what i say as a
philosopher looking at science
it is a splintering
of ddd cognitive science enterprise in a
variety of groups
each with its own peculiar research
tradition
and i think that that is basically fine
if no one has a
strong call or a strong argument or a
strong model that
does what newton did for physics and
unifies everything under a single banner
plurality is fine
so
there is no qualities more something
like well that's reality let's try to
like it
i'm
on board with that
but with this banner
what
shape would it be or how would we know
it when we saw it
i have no clue
we probably just
would just know it when we saw it in the
sense that we would see a research
tradition starting to
absorb
all others
uh
we would probably see
people trying to demonstrate us that
there is a real and significant
equivalence between
our
powerful research tradition uniform
research tradition and all the others
and probably the winning research
tradition the one that really got
cognition really got thinking
uh
would be able to make some novel
prediction that
no one else
was able to mate
and that would be probably a strong
marker that that's the way to go
if the implicit question is do i think
that
the free energy principle is that sort
of research tradition
i'm not sure
and my answer would probably be a
qualified no
because we
do not have
right now dddd
proof that is unifying as it wants to be
it makes big unifying claims
and it might be good in the sense that
they may foster cooperation at the very
least so you have at least that
pragmatic advantage
uh whether it's succeeding unifying
as
it wants to unify is still an open
question
and
and so the appropriate thing to do is to
for me at least to wait and see for
others perhaps is to
pick up your tools and try to unify and
show that it really is the right thing
or
just argue against even negative
arguments are useful right
uh non-action is an action that's true
in world knowledge traditions and also
in bayesian statistics like it can be
useful to wait to gather more
information
i wanted to return to what you said
earlier about
you need some boundaries
and a lot of this discussion of course
it's like extended how extended what is
extending and
what are we looking for with a boundary
model
in the fep and active world certainly we
talk a lot about
different kinds of blankets and bayesian
graphs and things like that but those
are not the only ways to think about
boundaries so just wanted to learn about
what are some other ways of thinking
about
boundaries cognitive boundaries of
different kinds and
what are you looking for in a boundary
model
not super sure about how to answer so
my understanding is that
markov blankets enter
into debate
as a sort of
tool to
understand what the boundaries of the
mind are
but there are no other
big alternative if not for something
said by chalmers about action and
perception
intuitive boundaries of the mind
but what i think he had in mind when he
said that was
something like look
our intuitive image of the mind is that
of something that is freeze between
perception and action
something like
we are
intuitively
predisposed to say that something like
the classical cognitive sandwich is true
we encounter reward for perception and
action
and
i'm not really sure whether
that sort of boundary would be a
boundary in the sense in which markov
blankets
would like to be boundaries or are used
to play the role of a boundary in the
sense of something that
individuates a single system and tells
it apart from anything else
the uh problem
i think for the extended mind and the
need for a boundary
is a need fueled by the strong desire
uh not to say that everything counts as
a cog in the cognitive machinery
why well because if everything counts as
a cognitive cognitive machinery then he
claimed that pen and paper used to do
more accounts
is not a big claim it doesn't add much
right
in order
to
for a claim well x is part of the
cognitive system to be meaningful to be
impactful
uh there must be things that are not
part of the cognitive system
otherwise i mean you're just claiming
well
there is this thing which is exactly
identical to any other thing
in the paper you uh you were threading
together this question of short and long
term features of cognition like in the
instantaneous action perception
cognitive behavioral time scale and then
the quote in the long run where a lot of
the arguments rest like it reduces
surprise in the long run or on average
in the long run and then you talked
about like um
jumping into
uh
it would force one to count inordinate
amount of stuff as a cog in someone's
thinking machinery jumping into ponds of
water while on fire or shooting at a
tiger to avoid becoming the tiger's
dinner both contribute to one's
prolonged occupation of one's phenotypic
states
but neither pawns of water nor guns and
bullets can be properly counted as cogs
in the thinking machinery and i can
totally see how
one type of extended mind perspective
would say like yes the boundaries of the
cognitive system are just so and they're
so flexible that whatever it is in the
situation that enables the cognition to
happen
is the cognitive system
at which point the lines are extremely
blurred with just
the system as it is
it's
like a pan
perspective
and
that
ends up
at least from a bayesian perspective not
being informative
because we no longer reduce our surprise
by learning about anything
and we've sort of deflated cognition
away
so
where does that sit with you is that a
goal like what are we
looking for in delineating cognitive
systems from each other
do we prefer pan-cognitivism do we
prefer
anti-pan cognitivism or do we want
something in between where like humans
are special or linguistic entities are
special
so i think that punk cognitivism should
be avoided
in general if you have punch something
ism
uh you are on bad road traveling down a
bad road because if everything counts as
x
uh there is nothing gained about from
calling things access no one is puzzled
by things in general i think
so that's the first point cognitive
cognitivism should be avoided
uh
what
i think is a designer atom many would
buy
is to have something balanced in between
uh
individualism
and ddd
i think appealing intuition that
sometimes interacting with stuff
at least aids cognition in a very
substantial way
so i think that
go through the zeratum would be to have
a bubble around dd
individual pretty radically understood
many would disagree many would be
comfortable with group vote with group
minds
i think that is a minority view
but maybe they're right i mean
being right or wrong is not a question
it's not a matter of numbers
but still to friendly debates i wouldn't
follow the minority view so i would keep
that option in the
theoretical horizon but not use it
to orient research right now
so what i would do is to have sort of a
bubble around the biological individual
and for the time scale
i think
that
the right thing to do again just to
frame things and get them started
is to focus on short time skills
the
hyper long evolutionary time scale
is not something that
captures our go-to intuitive sense of
cognition
and when you start framing a debate you
start from your go to intuitive native
standpoint
so my sympathy is for short times
for here and now
it's very funny like um
you mentioned you know it's not a vote
a small group of people could be um
correct and a larger group could be
incorrect yet people often think about
voting as group cognition
yet cognition isn't
a vote so that's kind of an interesting
tension there
um
let me ask about section five
so it's is vehicle externalism
conditioned over markov blankets
possible and you said i want to argue
that resorting to markov blankets to
settle the debate over vehicle
externalism leads us to sidestep the
whole debate in a very real sense making
vehicle internalism
vacuously true so
just for like a little context what is
vehicle externalism and internalism like
what is the distinguishing features of
these
uh concepts why are people interested in
this debate and like what does it matter
for talking about cognitive systems
okay so
uh externalism and internalism are
things that pop up everywhere in
philosophy and
here we go to with the vehicle variety
uh which is internally more externalism
about the and the thinking
machinery about the material stuff that
does the thinking say
and the
[Music]
you need to have a boundary in mind to
say internal and external and the go-to
boundary is the scan basically the skin
of the biological individual folks he
understood
internalism would be inside the skin
so cognition
or vehicle internalism is the idea that
the machinery of thought is inside your
skin and more precisely inside your
cranium
externalism is that at least some pieces
of that machinery are outside in pen and
paper cell phones whatever you want
but notice here we have an intuitive
boundary which is this game
if you go with mark of blankets
i think you end up called in a dilemma
because
you either
start with some intuitive marker blanket
say at the skin use it to define
internal and external
and then you might discover something
external to that blanket counts as part
of the system
or you can do what
again yakul power effect did which is
well
first i find the markov blanket of that
thing
the real one the mark of blanket with
the capital m
and then use that blanket to define what
is internal and what is external
and if you do that clearly
everything that matters is internal by
how you have defined internal
which is the one horn on the other hand
you start with the
standard
intuitive distinction between internal
and external
and then try to find a mark of blankets
which is fine but then the mark of
blanket does no longer distinguish
between internal and external
or
there is a tension there are two senses
of internal and you need to disentangle
the two the intuitive one and the markov
blanket
relative to the real market market one
and that is not what
seems to be going on in the literature
right
so basically that is my problem which is
a purely philosophical problem i think
is a purely philosophical note
but still
my concerns were philosophical
so it counts
[Music]
fair enough um is is that what you were
referring to when you said um
i doubt such a redefinition of
internalism would buy the internalist
something more than a purely verbal
victory
yes that's exactly the point i mean
the intern the vehicle internalists want
at the end of the day to say something
like this
thinking happens in the brain
or close to it
if you go on the markup blanket path uh
define internal in terms of a markup
blanket and then discover that the mark
of black contains the brain but also the
spinal cord but also my hands but also
pen and paper but also my cell phone and
so on and so forth
you can say well all that stuff is
internal so internalism is true
but i mean
that's a verbal victory
that is not one what you wanted to say
at the beginning right
that is a form of externalism that gets
passed as internalism because of how you
have defined your terms
and notice that even if you go with that
definition of internalism
then there would be still say super
internalists that say no no the real
internal thing that does the thinking is
just a brain and
externalist and journalist or relaxing
journalist that say no no no it's the
brain plus other internal stuff within
that
markup blanket
so
the problem wouldn't be close you would
still have a clash about
cerebralis and non-cerebralis if you
prefer people that thinks that
it's just the brain or the brain plus
the spinal cord and
people that like external stuff
doing part of the thing
it makes me think of um
like a
thought experiment kind of like a tracer
so like a radioactive tracer might be
injected in a blood vessel then you can
see where it flows or like a um a
metabolic label might be given to a cell
and then you can see how it gets
metabolized so
the tracer um let's just say we're
following like we're gonna pluck one of
the strings and trace the impact of like
shining light on the retina
initially
it follows like
nervous system paths but then let's say
that light pattern induces
the system to pick up that phone and
reload a website so now that tracer is
spreading everywhere it's calling
servers in different parts of the world
and it's like communicating through
satellites and it's like that
perturbation on the retina as
space and time sort of zoom out it's
like more and more gets wrapped into
that and so like what i'm hearing you
say is if we just say well wherever the
tracer goes
that's internalism internalism is the
total cognitive apparatus including the
satellite and the server in the other
country
or one could like retreat back
to the epithelial boundary
and just say like
it is
extended once they
are everything outside of the skin is
external
so it's sort of like again no one denies
that somebody could see something on
their retina that causes a server
far away to do something
but
where is our implicit or explicit
boundary
and will we just
stay with the epithelium which gives us
a
boundary
but then over different time scales
clearly different parts of that
total apparatus matter
um like over one seconds maybe um
the the oculomotor cicading
and the some brain region is involved
with processing meaning but then over
hundreds of years
there might be a more valid discussion
about how
it's actually interactions amongst
people
and slower
reading and writing
of like books or of other resources that
actually contribute to like the semantic
discussion and evolution
um
so it's it's like infuriating sometimes
because
again no one's saying that
what's on the table
isn't that way
it's just like what are we really
looking for in a cognitive theory
and what are we gaining or what kind of
value are we adding with these different
framings
yeah so
again to kick thing off i think that i
would stay close to the
basic individual i would
put the go to boundary at the scan
[Music]
and then
wait and see how things able from that
there is an important sense however
in which ddtdc
privilege of the scan uh putting the
boundary there at the scan
is
inadequate in the sense that
really if you look at us from a longer
perspective
perhaps as a species
you notice that
much on the of defense we do are
extremely dependent on how our
environment is our tools
and our niche
totally understood
it's just that due to
perhaps evolutionary reasons perhaps
cultural reasons
we tend to attach minds to
single bodies
say
and we have an expectation one body one
mind
once that expectation is in place you
can discover that the mind extends and
that pen and paper and yourself on and
so on and so forth
really help you think and really should
be considered part of the machinery that
does your thinking
if you don't have that expectation in
place
it's very hard to understand what
the extended mind could be for you
because there is no boundary relative to
which
there is an extension
right
you can't go farther farther than what
exactly you just will have the mind
cognition as it is in the real world
and once you have that it makes little
sense to say oh it's extended it might
be extended relative to the individual
to the biological body
but if you don't have expectation that
the two things go hand in hand
you don't have the violation of
expectation when you discover that they
don't go hand in hand you don't have the
sense of discovery
it's just
nothing strange happening that nothing
to be
amazed about nothing requiring anger
so that's a nice point
but as a matter of fact we
have the expectation that minds are
attached to individuals
so
there is a sense of wondering talking
about the extended mind something that
strikes us
of course a lot to
say there and connect back to like what
you mentioned about the cultural priors
um but sort of to
hinge on the cultural priors and go in a
slightly different way
how does this relate to
computationalism or
cognition and computers
not just us using computers to have like
a human-to-human convo but
what
does computationalism
add in to this discussion or how would
you relate what you discussed in the
paper
to computational theories of cognition
i'm not super sure so
i think
i think i think that combination is
computational but i'm not super sure
but if asked without any reflection i
would say yes of course cognition is
computation
uh so i think i count as a computation
i see no big problem in extended
computations
in the sense that
if you think about computation as symbol
manipulation or manipulation rule-based
or rule sensitive manipulation of
certain primitives that might be symbols
or
sub symbols or whatever
clearly you can have root based
manipulation of stuff outside your body
there is an historical point which
everyone i think knows that is well
originally computers were people doing
the math with pen and paper
uh before the second world war before dg
cell computer came about so there is
nothing intrinsically strange about
extended computation and computation
taking place outside your body
that being said
it
is true that most i would say
computational models focus on the brain
and that most of cognitive scientists
think that the really interesting
computation happens in between the two
years
then you have i mean rodney brooks
which surely is one of the inspirator of
and
prime movers of embodied cognition
anti-representational cognitive science
and and that really has inspired
extended cognition or at least the
strand of extended cognition
his mobiles were entirely computational
we're finding stage automaton for the
most part
so you don't what i would like to say is
that you don't necessarily have a clash
in between computation and
extended embodied cognitive science
as for
computational models of wider agent
environment systems
i know there are
on the top of my fingers
or on the top of my head i
i don't have any examples
but
i can gather them if
i were to remember by my uh by my artist
but there are such models and i think
that
there should be no in-principle problems
of making a free energy model about
the agent environment system or even
extended cognition indeed i think that
fristen clark kearsev and someone else
wrote a paper about that
with a
quick minimum model
not sure about the title that i think is
published on my language if someone
wants to check
this kind of uh it cracked me up with
the the freudian slip with the pluralist
slip you said at the top of my fingers
the top of my head and it's like
aren't those the different worlds though
and so it's it's just like very
interesting and it again comes back to
the um the water we swim in
the cultural priors and biases that
help us like shape whether an idea is
kind of outside of the overton window
like rocks can't think versus like
you're a heretic if you don't think that
rocks think
um
as we sort of
move towards a little fractal resolution
of course
this will probably be a um
discussion for many years to come so you
provided a quote from kirchoff and
kirsten 2019
um
i'm not going to read the whole quote
but it's visible on the stream and
basically they just mentioned that the
markov blanket formalism as applied to
systems that approximate bayesian
inference or we could even take it one
more instrumental level to systems that
we approximate with bayesian inference
serves as an attractive statistical
framework
in their case for demarcating the
boundaries of the mind but um other
situations as well and then you
mentioned like perhaps this is the
correct way to think about the role
markov blankets should play in the
debate over vehicle externalism
may be asking where can we draw a markov
blanket around the thinking machinery
yields more satisfactory results than
trying to find the mark of the cognitive
so um
this is really like a really nice point
and like what kinds of questions
help us move forward as we do seek like
productive but also you useful and
accessible ways to think about these
topics
what sort of question moves forward
yeah i have no idea probably
the only sensible answer is
ask questions and try to solve them
some will
and your retrospective you will be able
to identify the ones that really pushed
you forward from the ones that were not
well posed
so probably
the only sensible question to which
uh the only sensible answer is uh wait
and see
uh as for
ddd kiershov and keith steinhortz
i'm not super
so
a big
problem i had with mark of blankets
and extended mind is this
is
to me at least not super clear
whether when market blankets are used
the market blanket is something out
there in the world
like
some mathematical entity instantiated
somehow
in the world
or whether they are some sort of
accurate representation of what is going
on
or whether they are just
a mathematical tool to make sense of
what is going on
it seems to me that
those three things are used together
uh when it comes to discussing the
boundaries of the mind
but there are three different things i
mean there are
three different ideas about what a
marker blankets are
and by
adhering to one coherently you have a
very different
outlook
a
and a very different
metaphysics say of the free energy
principle
if market blankets are things out there
in the real world
then it seems that you must take the
free energy story at face value
you must be
an hardcore realist about the free
energy principle
if they are just a tool you can take the
free energy principle to be just perhaps
a sort of
mathematical machinery you can deploy to
build interesting models
of phenomena you want to study you can
try just as you can
use standard computational theory to
build models of things you can use the
free energy principle or you can use
dynamical system theory you have various
tools you can deploy
but
the
point is that
if you go super
instrumentalist oh that's just a model
and i do what i
want with it
my only guide is not truth but
pragmatic discoveries and making science
grow if you take that stance on the free
energy principle
you're forced not to make strong
metaphysical claims about d boundaries
of the minds and how things are you can
make strong and interesting claims about
how things are modeled
but not about how things are on the
other hand if you go super realist
you can make strong claims about how
things are
[Music]
but you also have a very strange
outlook on reality i think
with these sort of fractal boundaries
within boundaries
that are recycled reciprocal and so on
and so forth
my
two cents would be that
to follow the
pragmatic non-realist
usage of the free energy principle to
take it as a model building
tool
uh
but don't trust me
there are mighty sense and
i'm not super savvy
about
instrumentalism and model
definitely this
question or tension of instrumentalism
and realism kind of map and territory
in mel andrews 20 21 paper and several
other times we've seen this discussion
uh arise of course is
active inference just a statistical
model that we can apply to action
cognition perception just like we could
apply a linear model to height and
weight but that doesn't make height and
weight a linear regression so does
applying the active inference structure
to
neurobehavioral data
that cannot be taken as positive
evidence that that system for example is
doing active inference so um that's
definitely a um a point well taken and
the pragmatic turn
which is associated in cognitive science
with
a movement towards action orientation
and then there's like this meta
pragmatic turn in cognitive science
which is like
better theories are more useful
and that actually is um
in contrast with
what we were speaking about earlier with
science as
providing
explanations predictions
because the pragmatism actually
highlights the ability to design and
control it's like well if i used the
epicycles to
explain predict design control
it's useful enough
and
that
in a pragmatic world
would be sufficient but then somebody is
always coming out of um left field or
right field or whatever with the
questions about how things actually are
in singapore but they're not actually
moving
um
in that way
yeah i perhaps
do not see the ddd
any strong clash between pragmatism and
ureadism
what you definitely have here
are two say tendencies one to be
hyperplatonic and say look
reality is this way
there is nothing in your data that can
prove me wrong
which
is
even even respectable sometimes for a
certain class of entities like
mathematical entities
and the opposite tendency to say
i don't really care about how things are
i just care about prediction and control
and making good science and
predicting stuff and making discoveries
i think that a sensible observation is
that
typically
theories and models that
tends to to make discovery and
give you good prediction
have a degree of
accuracy tend to capture something about
how things are
i mean
you cannot
proceed arbitrarily
in model building and do whatever you
like
you have some sort of resistance and
intuitively i'd say that resistance is
reality
and so even
going fully pragmatism
prediction and control only
you get something about reality
maybe what is lacking is the
sort of platonic ideal reality that is
super independent about what you know
but i mean
that is something you encounter rarely
and only when you do philosophy
so if it gets left behind might not be
the biggest tragedy
of the human intellectual history that's
in this way
um
so one thought um is that in active
inference the way that we think about
action selection policy selection is as
related to
providing pragmatic value which like
brings you into alignment with your
preferences and then epistemic value
which reduces your uncertainty
and it's almost like
the utility
is loaded on the pragmatic side
but of course just narrowly pursuing the
pragmatic value
ends up leading into a blind corner
and so it's good to um balance both and
to have like diversity of thought within
a person within a scientific community
um we don't need to be 100
convinced um or only on one side of the
line as individuals or in a
collaboration
and then um to connect that to one other
point that you made in the paper so it's
on um
not sure if there's page numbers but
it's um
there should be page numbers
but there are
but there aren't
so i think it's the
online version and so without yeah
yeah exactly
um
so you were
talking about benchmarks that
adjudicate whether something counts as a
constituent of the thinking machinery
and so that's like something we've been
talking about so then
uh
you wrote traditionally this benchmark
is provided by the mark of the cognitive
that one endorses
again relate to what we've been
discussing that is by what one
implicitly or explicitly
takes to be necessary or sufficient to
make something a genuine contributor to
thinking in the broadest sense
so then i'm thinking about this paper
so it's a single author paper
however
you mention like in a footnote like
this observation and the example are due
to chris delega
you mentioned
in the acknowledgements
some people's names their citations
which is of course in science how we
communicate like attribution of ideas
and then there's even like a little
discussion with a reviewer
and so it's like there's all these
different
contributions actually
to this
cognitive artifact this epistemic
artifact
and so um it's like the like you're
you're supporting the biological
individual epithelial boundary single
author paper all these external
contributors like they can get mentioned
but they're not authors and then um like
if it were going to be written by the
radical pan-cognitivist
like why not make everyone an author
just
let's have everybody
as a contributor
and so just sort of like a funny little
microcosm there
no
no one not even the hyper radical would
put everyone as
an author because no one likes
the academical suicide no
i tend to privilege dd individual
boundary but i mean i am pro extension
at the end of the day i think i
mentioned it in the paper that
i am in favor of cognitive extension
and perhaps because i want cognitive
extension to be real i favor some
conservative boundary which is easily
transfast
this is perhaps more psychoanalysis
about my choices and my preferences
but yes i mean
i'm
on board with gddr that
you can have
cognitive processes that are that run
through multiple brains
i'm not super sure what how common they
are
because even
unless you do some real extreme
brainstorm
typically
the input coming from others is very
limited
or
not very sizable
but
i mean
there are
i would say genuinely
multi-brain cognitive processes
like a conversation
yeah like very deep conversations
uh in which at the end of the day you
agree
you do bring about some
uh
well-defined
artifact or output
just free-floating conversation i
wouldn't say that is a
a genuinely extended cognitive process
but
if you want to know there is a paper by
yelebrarinebug and regina fabre in which
they take all the
extended mind stuff
with mind wandering
and that is fascinating because
mind wondering
is clearly a cognitive process it's
clearly thought with the capital of t i
would even say
uh but isn't
not something that has a definite output
there is no
sad endpoint to mind wondering
right and yet they claim they might it
might extend
and if you take this sort of no set
output no set endpoint perspective then
maybe even converse causal conversation
may qualify
as
intrapersonal cognitive processes
but i'm not super sure about
how one could
develop that idea
precisely
it it kind of makes me think about um
in a very transposed analogical way like
to integrated information theory like if
two people are speaking at each other
but they're both having the conversation
that they would have with a wall
then it's like they're speaking past
each other it's not like an emergent
conversation whereas if people are
engaged in like active listening
and like actually
integrating some novel stimuli and then
coming up with something they wouldn't
have said to a wall
then that is like where that that third
space arises where things can be
productive but then also that's very
interesting that they might not be and
one one other note on the mind wandering
is um
as our technology in the niche changes
with some neural recording
opportunity
say just let your mind wander
and all of a sudden through biofeedback
or the enabling of new cognitive
linkages
that mind wandering actually could leave
a trace
on the environment in a way where
if it's
just brain bound it um
wouldn't
which i think returns us to that earlier
question just like that one
thing i wanted to address about like
composition of cognitive systems so
whether we're
internalist or externalist or whatever
how do we think about this space of the
adjacent possible
for cognitive systems like what can we
think of next
what can we think of next or how could
we think differently if there were some
structural changes
to our environment
like the pen until it existed or the
writing implement until it existed
wasn't there and there was
pre-adaptations and evolutionary basis
for utilizing it etc
but when it was there it
changed the game in a quantum way so how
do we think about those kinds of
transformations of cognition
i'm super not an expert
about this topic
and i'm a bit ashamed i guess
frankly but i
and i need to catch up
but i think it is
probably strongest case study you could
make for transformation
is with reading and doing math
we have
of course busy visual capacities
but reading
seems to be
a purely cultural thing
something that you need culture to to
learn and something that deeply
transforms your
cognitive abilities so just
the ability to
target
your own thought crystallized in a
written form
gives you a level of meta reflection
that would be
hard to maintain with your brain alone
or the ability to crystallize your
thoughts in a scrap of paper
leave it there
two to ferment and then go back at it
one week later two weeks later three
weeks later with a fresh mind
this sort of thing is not something you
can do without
externalizing your thought
you can just remember your passports
and
objectively look at them as you
objectively look at your past four
written paper
and the other thing of course is math
we have some basic familiarity with
numbers that is biologically endowed
uh but
pretty much from arithmetic on it is
all bootstrapped by culture
and of course here you have the biggest
transformation
possible with
mathematical objects
uh modeling and all sort of things so
those would probably be the case studies
to to try and have a sense of what ddd
space of the decent possible mind might
be
uh
and this is pretty
backward looking
i'm trying really hard right now to
think something more forward-looking
something more
propositive something more
hands-on let's build a new mind but i
don't have any idea right now
um about that
we'll like look back to look forward
it's an it's an interesting idea and
theme i you know of course wish you luck
on the forward-looking but when you
talked about asking questions
um
it made me write down and subsequently
remind myself later
either the question
will have been asked already
doesn't mean that it's been
satisfactorily answered
to anyone or to you but either the
question has been asked in its
rhetorical structure
and then it'd be awesome to point people
towards a knowledge resource or it's a
novel question
and novel questions are awesome and then
looking back it may be possible to know
which of those novel questions led to a
useful
line of discussion or application
but
to
wait before the question
and say well i only want to ask the best
question
it's like
in a way we
don't know since it's so many steps down
the road from the question at least one
or two
till we can evaluate
the impact of the question and so um
like
as a hack or a heuristic
um
[Music]
having
rigorous scholarships so that when the
questions have been asked we're not
doing truly redundant work but then also
like recognizing and raising up new
questions
helps
expand the frontier and the fringe
and some fraction of those may develop
into useful avenues and then later on
people might say well it was obvious
somebody should have connected
the sequential database with the
encryption and with an economic system
but those things existed long ago
and it's like looking back that some of
the synthesis
conceptually or technologically
um
post hoc
make more sense but again waiting
and not acting for it to make sense
a priori it's like it
it doesn't seem like just a 2022 thing
that that's not gonna work that seems to
be like in principle a very challenging
way
to expect effective action
yeah i'm not super sure i got the point
so
uh jdr
would be this
that you don't have any sort of
precognition about where a question will
lead you
you cannot evaluate questions beforehand
before asking them to see oh this person
right here
a long way to go it's a good one and
this other is
waste of time
right is that the point
yeah even if there was no um yeah we
shouldn't uh pre-judge
questions we could easily sort questions
into those that have already been asked
and those that have not been asked
and so to those that have been asked we
can use scholarship to those that have
been asked we can like recognize novelty
um
so even we don't need to finesse that
too much and just to kind of connect
that however vaguely to your idea of
like looking back
but then the challenge of looking
forward in cognitive sciences sometimes
yeah it's truly a challenge
but i think it's per
a big challenge for me because i'm
eloquent to look forward in cognitive
science if you probably ask people that
do
build cognitive architectures and
cognitive models for a living
i think they would be much more
forward-looking than me
i mean um you have something you'd like
to try is a twist on the architecture
you'd like to put and that is i think
forward-looking right
well what is your
forward looking like
over whatever time horizon or
capacity set that makes sense like what
kinds of questions or experiments or
research areas
are you like excited to build on from
this paper
i'm not super sure where this paper is
headed
i mean
i'll continue probably to work on
extended minds
i
still think i'll be working on
predictive processing in a sort of very
vapid fashion
probably i'll try to merge d2
in a more positive way probably
but i'm not super sure probably in
computational terms
but this is super big it's super what i
want to do
with my postdoc if i had one
nice it's not because
a concrete proposal right now
hypothetical postdocs are the best
this is the list of wishes what i wish
to do well i wish to do
yeah probably that's
that would be one thing and another
thing i'd like to to do is to try and
say open up and specify the grip
metaphor you have andy clark
and
those other people telling you
what predictive processing slash dp3
energy principle gives you is a grip on
the affordances that matter
is
not super clear what the grip is
apart from
not stumbling into things and moving
around appropriately
the epistemic sort of contact with the
war
is left i think unanalyzed
but i have no big idea on how to analyze
it
it makes me think about how um words
related to our physical cognition and
describing our interior landscape like
get a grip
um you know can you see what i'm
thinking about or let me sketch it out
for you comprehension means to grasp
with a hand so like there's so many and
of course the whole optimal grip
active inference as getting grip on
things from a physical perspective like
as the hand goes for the cup of coffee
but then okay now we transpose that into
the cognitive
space
and we
in a conversational way do talk about
grip
and then
here's all of these formalisms that it
can be hard to get a grip on
but are they about grip or like what
would that actually mean that's very
interesting question
yeah i mean
there is
a way to impact the grip idea in terms
of beijing in france
but that is a bit too internalized for
my likings the idea that perception is a
form of inference that you are inferring
every time everything
it works in the model domain the model
is infrared
whether you think itself is inferential
i'm not super sure and i'm
i'm not sold on ddr that's the
inferential talk
really captures what goes on in most
instances of cognition
i mean
most of our thought is not described
inferentially when i let my mind go and
start mind wondering not inferring
things at random i mind wondering
when i grow an impress i draw an
influence typically with
high concentration to one specific topic
and usually dedicated pen and paper
so the inferential talk might not be
optimal but still
i
feel the need to do
to give some sort of epistemic
connotation to the grip isn't is not
just not stumbling into things and
moving around quickly and swiftly there
is some sort of comprehension and
intelligence and mindfulness into that
that going with a pure
good behavior
good behavior of patterns vocabulary
might not just miss but
it might even
let you open to the charge of being a
behaviorist of being
a philosophical zombie without any inner
life
and that sort of things we need some
mentalistic lexicon some epistemically
charged lexicon
which is not
full dom d card
and a major challenge would be to
develop it
it makes me think about like an ocean
and the river and then where they meet
and it's brackish
cognition and pure cognitive the rest
cognitive and then there's the
physicalism
and um
[Music]
we have the ability to like be uncertain
actually and to evaluate and to
oscillate between different perspectives
or different regimes of attention on
these different ideas like
more highlighting the physical
boundaries of a system more highlighting
the cognitive
more highlighting the statistical causal
which is where the markov blanket
concept comes from from pearl
and bayesian causal graphs and those
causal graphs
the nodes and the edges
may or may not link to anything that is
a physical thing or a cognitive thing
so it's a very um
[Music]
open and interesting
area
um
is there anything else that you like
wanted to just bring up talk about ask
no i don't think
so i think it's now time to thank you
for the space the opportunity and the
wonderful talk
to thank the dd audience which i not
seen because i can only see you
apparently from my screen but hi
audience i hope you enjoyed it
i hope you
didn't found me too rambling
if they're listening this far then i
don't think either of us are too rambly
for them
oh maybe they are just
doing exercise driving around and want
some steady background
without killing friends
awesome well yeah marco
thanks for the
paper and the contribution and for
joining for a guest stream you're always
welcome to continue the discussion and
also thank you for all of those who
listened and paid attention for this
conversation
great
okay see you later
see you later bye everyone
you